And now it's time for the juiciest bit
of all in this unit, and that's the hot
smoking turd that was politics in the
guilded age. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so let's start with guilded age
politics on the national level. And
there are three things you need to know.
First, the two major political parties
should sound familiar to you, namely the
Republicans and the Democrats. And
essentially, these parties appealed to
the lingering divisions that the Civil
War had created. Now, Democrats were
mainly southerners, though not
exclusively, who championed states
rights and racial segregation, and they
could usually count on the votes from
big city political machines and the
growing population of immigrants, on
which more in a moment. Now,
Republicans, on the other hand, were the
northern more industrial party who could
count on votes from black people and the
middle class and businessmen and
Protestants. But then the second thing
you need to know is that one of the main
features of national politics during
this time was constant stalemate. In
other words, federal politicians didn't
get much done. And that's because for
the closing decades of the 19th century,
the House and Senate were controlled by
opposing parties who constantly opposed
each other. Additionally, the majorities
each party held in their respective
houses were real thin, and since voter
turnout was super high, it led to fierce
competition to remain in office. And
then the third and most salacious
characteristic you need to remember
about guilded age politics is that it
was corrupt. So various reformers
claimed that corruption had seeped into
every level of government and therefore
politicians no longer represented the
people, but rather their own economic
greed and self-interest. And look, there
were certainly some politicians who
attempted to keep things above board,
but for the most part, these reformers
were right. Like during this time, since
there were no laws that prevented
politicians from receiving payments from
large corporations, it was pretty common
practice for them to understand their
elected position as a way to gain wealth
for themselves. For example, the
railroad tycoon Jay Gould liked to brag
publicly that he'd elected the entire
New York state legislature with his own
money. So in this way, owners of large
corporations paid congressional
politicians who would then vote in favor
of policies that would benefit those
corporations as had been common practice
in the expansion of the oil and steel
and railroad industries. In fact, the
1890 Congress became known as the
billiondoll Congress because they passed
the highest tariff bill in US history.
And those tariffs benefited the owners
of large corporations who can now
dominate the domestic market with their
lowerpriced goods. And then members of
Congress went positively hog wild
spending the excess federal funds
generated by the tariffs in order to
enrich themselves and their districts
with pet projects. And so the collection
of revenues in general created the
occasion for no small amount of
government corruption. And the poster
child for this development was the
crediier scandal. And the short version
is this. The Union Pacific Railroad
Company set up a front organization
called Kred Mobilier to pay for the
construction of one of the
transcontinental railroads. And through
that company, they charged far more for
the project than it cost and then
pocketed millions of dollars to enrich
themselves. And in order to keep that
corruption free from the intervention of
the stupid government, they bribed
members of Congress with shares in the
company in exchange for their uh
discretion. Okay, now here's where I
tell you that even though the federal
government was about as limp and
ineffective as a soggy earthworm, there
were at least three issues that got them
all stirred up. The first issue was the
patronage system, which was the method
by which the president filled federal
jobs after his election. You see, the
way patronage worked is that when a
candidate won the presidency, for
example, he would sit at his desk for
months hearing from thousands of callers
who lined up out the door looking for
federally appointed jobs because they
had been a supporter of that candidate.
And you might remember Andrew Jackson
being the poster child of the patronage
system, which he called the spoil system
because to the victor, go the spoil. And
so for years, politicians had attempted
to reform the patronage system, but all
that congressional stalematey stuff that
I mentioned earlier prevented any
meaningful reform. However, the practice
came under serious fire after the
assassination of President James
Garfield. You see, after winning the
election, Garfield sat in his office
hearing from thousands of men seeking
jobs. And as it turned out, a guy
Garfield decided to pass on got a little
cranky and his eye got all twitchy with
rage. And so, he went ahead and
assassinated Garfield at a train station
a few months later. And I suppose the
lesson we learned was this. Always hire
the guy with the twitchy eye because if
you don't, he's going to shoot you.
Anyway, in order to correct the spoil
system mess, Congress passed the
Pendleton Act of 1881. And basically it
replaced the patronage system with a
competitive examination. If you wanted a
federal job, you had to compete for
scores with all the others on this exam.
And the highest scores got the job. And
this seemed to be a win for democracy.
But it kind of petered out because of a
shift in philosophy and how parties were
funded. You see, prior to this,
candidates were funded by the party
faithful, which is why they felt they
were owed jobs. And now they shifted to
receiving funding from a handful of
wealthy individuals. And so the
debt-based patronage system wasn't
nearly as binding as it was previously.
But then the second big debate between
the parties had to do with currency. You
see, at this point, the United States
Treasury was on the gold standard. And
that meant that when the Treasury issued
paper money, there was a corresponding
amount of real gold somewhere in a vault
that backed up that paper. And as you
may or may not know, there is only a
limited amount of gold in the world. And
so, if the government only prints money
that is tied to the gold supply, that
means that the money supply will be
pretty limited. And look, for the stupid
rich people at the top of the heap, that
arrangement was just fine because they
held a significant amount of those
goldbacked dollars in their own
accounts. But some politicians,
especially those who represented western
states that were full of indebted
farmers, pushed to expand the money
supply by adding silver coinage. And
that would have been great for
Westerners because not only was there a
whole lot of silver in western states,
but introducing silver would lead to
inflation or the rising of prices. And
that means when they sold their goods on
the market and got paid, they could then
more easily pay off their debts with
inflated money. And that seemed like a
real good deal to them. And then the
third common debate among politicians
during this time was over tariffs and
whether it was appropriate to favor
American industries with such policies.
And since I mentioned that earlier, I'll
leave it there for now. But now, let's
get more local and look at how politics
played out at the city and town level.
Because for all the lethargy of the
federal government, it was the local
arena where most of the political power
was wielded. So at the city level,
political power was fragmented. But over
time, much of the power became
concentrated in the hands of
organizations known as political
machines. Now, these machines were
typically run by a boss who was also an
elected official. And his main goal was
to keep himself and his loyalists in
power. And how says you, did these
bosses keep themselves in power? Will
says, "I reach into those brainfolds and
see if you can remember who mainly lived
in industrial urban cities during this
time." And if you said immigrants and
the working poor, then gold star for
you. And I'm not going to go back over
what it was like to be a member of one
of these communities. But the short
version is that it was a pretty hard and
nasty life. And so these political
machines maintained their power by
providing expansive public welfare
services for immigrants and impoverished
workers. Things like food and coal for
the winter or jobs on public works
projects. But they didn't provide those
things because their hearts bled and
wept for the plight of the poor. No. In
exchange for those services, the bosses
expected the votes of the people whom
the machine helped. And that was way
easier to do during this time because
voting was public, not private. And so,
in that way, bosses were able to remain
in power and shape public policy to
their liking. But the bosses also enrich
themselves through the machines by
protecting illegal activities like
gambling and prostitution for a cut of
the profits. And of course, the most
well-known and notorious of these bosses
was Boss Tweed, seen here pioneering the
world's first Gen Z stare. Anyway, Tweed
led the machine at Tamony Hall in New
York and was able to gain enormous
wealth through corrupt practices. For
example, Tweed appointed himself to
oversee the construction of a courthouse
in Manhattan. And although the budget
for the building was around a quarter of
a million dollars, Tweed was able to
drive up the cost to around $13 million,
most of which ended up in his own
pocket. But eventually, Tweed's theft of
such enormous sums of taxpayer money was
discovered and he was convicted in jail.
But anyway, this was the flavor of local
politics during the guilded age. And the
truth is the operation of political
machines while certainly an example of
corruption was sort of a gray area
morally speaking. Like another Tammy
Hall boss called what they did honest
graph. In other words, yes, the machines
got things done by underhanded and often
illegal means, but the services they
provided to the working poor were a real
benefit to many of them. Well, okay, now
let's turn the corner and talk about the
rise of a new political party at the end
of the 19th century that was all kinds
of fed up with government corruption and
decided to do something about it. That's
right, it's time to meet the populist
party. Now the chief issue that defined
politics in the last decade of the 19th
century was the panic of 1893. It was a
severe economic depression caused mainly
by the bankruptcy of a large railroad
company and the subsequent failure of
banks that came afterward. And that
event happened to coincide with a deep
debt crisis among Western farmers. So
like I've said in previous videos, the
introduction of new agricultural
technologies like the combine harvester
had significantly increased the
productivity of American farms and that
meant the market was now flooded with
agricultural products which drove prices
down. And at the same time, farmers debt
was increasing rapidly and without
decent prices for their output, they
were unable to pay back their loans. And
so in 1892, the National Farmers
Alliance organized a new political party
called the People's Party, better known
as the Populist Party, in order to
address the economic suffering of
America's farmers. And the
organization's membership was largely
made up of many diverse groups who felt
the government was no longer working to
protect and advance their own interest,
groups like farmers and labor unions and
middle-class reformers and black
Americans, etc. And so they met in 1892
to formalize their party's principles.
and they laid it out in what became
known as the Omaha platform. And the
most significant policies in the
platform sought to reform both political
and economic reality. On the political
side, populist called for the direct
election of senators, which up to this
point had been the responsibility of
state legislators. Additionally, the
populace called for the increased use of
the referendum, which allowed ordinary
voters to steer government policy. And
then on the economic side, populist
called for an expanded coinage of silver
in order to address the debt crisis
plaguing farmers. Additionally, in order
to make taxation policy fairer, populist
called for a graduated income tax. The
idea was that people who made less money
would pay less a percentage of taxes
while the wealthy would pay a higher
percentage of taxes. And in this way,
wealth would be redistributed among
Americans in a more equitable way. And
then the platform also included
provisions for the government ownership
of railroads, federal loans for farmers,
and an 8-hour workday for the industrial
working class. Anyway, the point of all
these items on the Omaha platform was to
weaken the influence of the wealthiest
Americans who wielded an outsized
influence on the American economy and
politics and make the economy and
government more answerable to the common
people who composed the vast majority of
the population. Now, the populace did
not win the presidential election of
1892, but they were able to win several
congressional seats as well as electing
a handful of state governors and many
seats in state legislatores. Even so,
the next presidential election in 1896
would prove to be the end of the
populist party. So they nominated
William Jennings Bryan as their
candidate who was a strong advocate of
farmers as well as the expanded coinage
of silver. And Brian was a mesmerizing
orator who articulated the battlecry of
the populace and the desire for the
coinage of silver by proclaiming that he
would not allow businesses to crucify
mankind upon a cross of gold. Even so
the Republican William McKinley won the
election and that's largely because by
1896 the economic depression which had
provided all the energy for populist
reforms had essentially ended. And so
that combined with a great deal of
internal division in the party led to
its rapid demise. However, many of their
proposed political and economic reforms
would be accomplished in the next period
thanks to the progressive movement.
Okay, it's the end of the unit. If
you're studying for a test, you can
click here to grab my A pushheimler
review guide, which is the fastest way
to study. Or you can click here to watch
my other videos from unit 6. I'm glad
you came around and I'll catch you on
the flip-flop. I'm La.